welcome back to logic 101 I'm William
Spaniel and this lecture is on the rule
of inference known as the constructive
dilemma this one is a little bit more
complicated than previous rules of
inference we've seen because it involves
three three premises we have two
implications to start off with P implies
q and R implies s notice that we have
four simple sentences in total there and
they're split evenly across those two
premises so we have just p and Q up top
and just R and S down bottom there is no
overlap between those two the third
premise is the disjunction between the
antecedence of those two implications so
we have P or R and if we have all of
that then we can conclude that the
disjunction between the second half of
those two implications QRS is true as
well essentially what's going on here is
that we're applying modus ponin across
the various different cases that part
three gives us so part three premise 3
tells us that P is true or R is true or
both P and R are true well in the first
case suppose p is true then we have q
being true through line one and modus
ponents if we have the second case where
just R is true then through modus
ponents in line two we have S being true
and if both of them are true then
through modus ponents and lines one and
two we have both q and s being true and
that's exactly what we see with the
conclusion there we see Q or S being
true which means Q could be true or S
could be true or both of those things
could be true to see this in action with
an example suppose that premise one said
if I am running I am happy and premise
two said if I am sleeping I am dreaming
and finally premise three said I'm
running or I'm sleeping well if I'm
running then I'm happy if I'm sleeping
then I'm dreaming and if I'm running and
sleeping perhaps I'm running in my sleep
then I'm both happy and I'm Dreaming
which is exactly again what the
conclusion says I'm happy or I'm
Dreaming or both now normally what I've
been doing for these rules of inference
is then showing you that this is true on
a truth table but as I mentioned at the
top we have four different simple
sentences here and in the past we've
explored what it looks like when you do
a truth table with four simple sentences
and of course we have 1 2 3 four complex
or compound sentences here which are
only going to make things more
complicated so I'm actually going to
hold off on doing that truth table
because again it's pretty complicated
something that you might want to do on
your own and instead of showing you how
to prove it using a truth table instead
later on in this course when we've
learned how to do proof by contradiction
I will use proof by contradiction to
prove the constructive dilemma through
what actually is going to turn out to be
a much simpler process than a truth
table so of course you don't know how to
do this quite yet but by the end of this
course when we start getting into proofs
you will learn how to do this and I will
take you through this step by step so
you can see that constructive dilemma is
true not using of course constructive
Dilemma to arrive at that conclusion all
right I hope you enjoyed this and I hope
to see you here next time when we talk
about the modus tolan's version of the
constructive dilemma which is known as
the destructive dilemma hope you enjoy
this again and I hope to see you next
time take
care